all right
[Music]
four out of four studies on spicy food
and mortality found a significant
decrease in the risk of premature death
as I detailed in my last video
the intake of sweet peppers also seemed
to help but to a lesser extent so there
may be some benefit to the spicy
capsaicin compound itself I have a whole
section on Chili Peppers in my fat
burners chapter in how not to diet how
cayenne pepper can counteract the
metabolic slowing that accompanies
weight loss and accelerate fat burning
as a bonus so maybe the weight loss
benefits account for the mortality
benefits apparently not since there was
a mortality risk reduction with chili
pepper consumption even after
controlling for body mass index
maybe the spice was used as a
replacement for salt anything that
reduces sodium intake could improve
longevity as excess salt consumption is
the deadliest dietary risk factor the
worst thing about the human diet wiping
out millions of people every year
not only could you use the spice to
replace salt the spicy compound actually
makes things taste saltier than they
actually are sprinkling on some red
pepper powder can increase your salt
taste sensitivity so you can achieve the
same salty taste with less salt you can
put people on a pet scanner and pick up
differences in your secondary taste
cortex the part of your brain associated
with pleasure signaling to salty foods
so you can use hot peppers to hack your
brain for your health
and indeed those are the high spice
preference had lower salt intake in
better blood pressures and this again
appears to be independent of the
anti-obesity benefit of hot pepper
consumption though the lower risk of
developing high blood pressure among
those with higher hot pepper intake was
also independent of sodium intake so
there may be some other benefit Pathways
as well like maybe it also helps your
kidneys excrete more salt too though the
evidence to support this was derived
from studies on mice so who knows
however it works eating spicy foods or
adding supplemental spicy flavor to food
by like sprinkling on cayenne pepper or
hot sauce represents a novel lifestyle
intervention that can reduce both salt
intake and blood pressure
here are some examples of no salt added
hot sauces
even regular Tabasco is pretty low in
sodium though only the original flavor
some of the other spin-off flavors like
Buffalo habanero Chipotle have five
times more
now just because all studies on spicy
food and mortality to date suggest hot
peppers may help you live longer doesn't
mean you can go out and eat a ghost
pepper designated the Guinness book
hottest pepper in the world in 2007.
here's the peppers you may be used to
measured in the hundreds of thousands of
Scoville heat units some varieties of
habanero can be 50 times as hot as
jalapenos
to get to ghost peppers though you have
to switch over to millions of units
the ghost pepper beat out the habanero
in 2007 which itself got outshadowed by
the Trinidad scorpion in 2011 and then
2013 at Burning as the reigning champ
the Carolina Reaper
but just eating a ghost pepper which
this poor guy did as part of a contest
resulted in such violent vomiting he
ruptured his esophagus which is a
potentially life-threatening surgical
emergency the only thing hotter than the
reaper is pure pepper spray which can
lead to such violent coughing you can
rupture along
pepper spray in the eye only seems to be
a problem if you can't wash it out this
woman was pepper sprayed and handcuffed
Away In A Cell for nine hours and
appears to have suffered permanent
damage to her vision the best thing you
can do if you're trying to help someone
spray it in the face is to try to calm
them down make sure they're breathing
okay remove their contact lenses as soon
as possible and then abundantly irrigate
their eyes to wash out the chemical
really abundantly as in washing their
eyes with water or saline for a full 10
to 20 minutes it's a long time to be
washing your eye out again after contact
lenses have been removed or even better
not worn to an event where you might be
pepper sprayed in the first place even
just ambient exposure to Pepper gas can
cause dry eye symptoms that last for
weeks even if you're not sprayed
directly
it's ironic that the chemical weapons
convention prohibits the use of these
riot control agents during Warfare yet
they are routinely used to quell
civilian protests
the most serious eye injuries though are
Trauma from fired projectiles like
pepper balls leading to the suggestion
that protesters wear ballistic eye
protection recommending that medical
centers proactively reach out to protest
leaders and participants regarding
appropriate safety precautions
in terms of what you can do for pepper
spray irritation on your skin there are
anecdotal reports that baby shampoo is
helpful however as yet there have been
no published scientific studies that
demonstrate their effectiveness
until
now baby shampoo to relieve the
discomfort of tear gas and pepper spray
exposure a randomized controlled trial
police recruits received a burst of
pepper spray to the face then were
randomized to washing off with water or
water along with some Johnson and
Johnson baby shampoo and
it didn't work at all
how about using Maalox or a numbing
lidocaine gel or milk nothing beat out
plain old water copious water
decontamination is the preferred method
of pain control after topical pepper
spray exposure
anyways that was quite the tangent
bottom line should we all begin taking
tablets of capsaicin and dousing our
food with hot sauce if you like hot
sauce go for it but I don't think we
should start taking supplements until we
have randomized controlled trials
proving benefit
oh